all right so guess what I deleted my
temp directory so don't be me I do stuff
in temp all the time because I don't
have to clean it up when I reboot my
computer but I had to reboot my computer
because I wanted to be really fast and
have a you know no packet loss even
though I've already had a few drop
frames I can't explain it anyway so what
do we do we avoid that now it was a
stupid little script so I don't mind
losing it but you probably do so let's
do this I haven't covered this yet in
the beginner of boost but we're going to
cover in at least this time but we're
going to go ahead and cover it so if you
do not have a GitHub account pause the
video right now and go add a GitHub
account unless you're under 13 in which
case go talk to your parents about what
to do if you add an account and you
GitHub and you're under 13 it's not my
fault right it's against the child
online protection act and it's illegal
big time in fact every violation of that
every single time you use a service and
you're under
13 you can be fined
$16,000 for each time you access the
service so you know I'm not telling you
to do that if you do that you're it's on
you but you know that being said if
you're 13y old and or you want to live
dangerously or whatever then we're going
to use GitHub why because we're going to
save our code we're going to figure out
a place to save our code so that we can
put it up there and it's up there for us
to go get any time okay um I will make a
separate video about how to use a bare
git repository as your backup instead of
GitHub but let's be real GitHub is the
place for you to do it if you have
access to it okay so go the first step
one is to go create your account on
GitHub don't do anything else until
you've done that once you have the
account on GitHub make it lowercase by
the way something you're going to
remember preferably the same name as
what you have on your computer and then
once you have that done let's go ahead
and look at what comes next so this
comes down to organizing your repository
into a way you can get through
everything you can see a bunch of stuff
this is a Mac it's a Unix machine that's
got all these things if you're on a
Linux machine a lot of times you have
these same initial uppercase letters um
I don't mind that I it does bother me a
little bit because it's not Unix but it
doesn't matter that's the way
everybody's decided to do it whether it
be Mac windows or Linux
wsl2 doesn't have anything in there uh
but you know if you're in your windows
home directory you do you have the same
thing so these they're not standardized
but they're the same but the thing
that's nice about that is then your
scripts can do the same thing so I have
a script like for example move last it
automatically looks into the downloads
directory on any of these systems
assuming the downloads directory has a
capital D and based on that preference I
went ahead and made something called a
repos directory so inside of the repost
directory um let's just look inside of
the repost directory
oh my gosh there's a lot of stuff there
yeah well that's probably not the thing
to do because repost does have all the
get repos and tree does not eliminate
those so whatever um anyway so there's a
bunch of stuff there so let's CD into
repos and you can see github.com and
then inside of github.com you see a
number of other places like these are
all the people that I've cloned from in
the past um and I have an automatic
script for that I'll show you about
later and then so we go into GitHub
and then you'll see mine in here as well
uh RX Rob and you'll see that there okay
so let's make that here's how you do
that make
d-p oops make sure you use your exact
name of your of your GitHub repo uh
repos SLG up.com rwx Rob in my case
whatever yours is and then that'll make
it for you okay now we're going to go
back into it so we're going to use the
history so if you're not using VI mode
for history which you should be then set
that show VI and then we're going to
push up you know go up in the history we
go back up again and now we have makor
I'm going to change these thing I'm
going to change those two words
C2 W and now oops it didn't change them
all it almost changed them all let's go
ahead and use it let's say now we're
going to CD CD space and then we're
going to X we're going to x that out and
then we're going to hit enter and that's
going to take us all the way down into
there so that trick about editing your
history using VI mode is really powerful
it's by far the fastest way it's way
faster than Zell and it's Universal it
works and any Unix system ever made so
you don't ever have to work worry about
zel not being on the box and having
stupid things in your muscle memory
because it'll just work so using set Das
Obi is very powerful and that's all I'm
going to say about that so now I'm in
the right place and I'm ping to see
where I am and there's nothing in here
in your case so the next thing to we
need to install git and GitHub in order
for this to work so I'm on a Mac so if
you're on a Mac it's Brew install git
and GitHub and that will go grab the
latest of git and the GH command line
tool so that'll get it for you if you're
on a Unix machine apt you do sudu appt
install get GitHub oops getting GH I am
not on a a Linux or WSL machine um so
I'm not going to do that okay but that's
what you would do that's the command
they're both included um you don't have
to do a custom PPA if you've seen my DOT
files that's no longer needed uh I spent
a lot of time figuring that out just now
so um okay so that's all you need for
that now once you have that you can GH
off
login and you hit enter and you can go
ahead and follow the steps to
authenticate when you get to GitHub you
hit GitHub https authenticate using HTTP
yes log to the web browser you hit yes
that's going to give you a code and then
it's going to say do you want to open
your web browser and you say yes and it
will pop open your web browser you
authenticate type in all the things and
then you hit you hit enter on that on
the or whatever you click on enter on
the website and it will come back and
it'll say huzzah you're authenticated
okay that's pretty basic stuff it's
really fast and easy Once you have that
you can do GH status and that will tell
you uh the status of
well wrong
thing that's cool
though that's like that's like a that's
like a a summary of all of my statuses I
I got to start using that
more what I meant to do is this the off
status so this tells you all the things
that don't you know there a token it
says hey I'm logged in in the old days
another way to do this if you just want
to use git is you can do SSH uh we've
been doing this for years get at
github.com and that will tell you that
you've been authenticated and that
you're ready to go um and it just you
know blocks yeah that's the old way of
doing it uh trying to docks real hard no
I'm not I knew that wouldn't docks so so
anyway so now we're all ready to go what
comes next all right so now we're going
to make a repo we're going to make your
dot files repo I'm not going to get into
why you have a DOT files repo you can go
do a search on on there for DOT files on
GitHub and you'll see there's tens of
millions of dot files it's like a write
of Passage to create your own dot files
directory that is normally the first
repo you're going to create if you don't
have one of those yet go ahead and make
it and start using that to put in you
know your configuration and stuff like
that and but now I'm assuming you've
already done that and you've got your
configurations kind of set up the way
you want you can kind of move them in
there and thing uh I will be covering
that in the book quite a bit but right
now that's just I'm not I'm skipping
that because we're working on bash so
the next thing we're going to do is
we're going to make another repo and
it's probably that you can have be the
same one if you want but I call this
repo lab and the reason I call it lab is
because it's where I put all my notes in
some people call it notes some people
call it a codebook some people call I
mean there's a million things you can
call it what it is is it's a combination
of code and it's basically your own
textbook right it's all your notes plus
all your code Snippets and everything
they're all it's all in there and it's
it's there for you to go in and peruse
and look at and try around and so you
have to decide if you want to make it
private or public if you want to share
it or not if it's going to represent
your best code for other people to see
or if it's just something you want to
just be able to dump random stuff in
there and not really give up where you
want to do there once you have decided
all of those things then you can go
ahead and make one now I've already got
one so I'm going to show you the command
for this so GH uh uh repo create uh--
private uh D- clone and I'm going to
create and we're going to call it uh
lab uh sample okay so mine is called you
can call it a Spellbook if you want yeah
uh so we're going to call it lab sample
okay so what did this this did a lot of
things all at once and I just want to
tell you it people say why are you using
GH for all that you have to teach
getting everything I'm like no I
don't you know how many people don't
know about this my entire team at work
has no idea every time I show them this
this is the comment they say I need to
learn that get up command I need to
spend some time to learn that yeah you
really do okay this is one of those
things where people are like why aren't
you learning the V language and I'm like
because I need to help people learn
about the kid command line tool which
has relevance there's people who are
learning V and nicks don't know how to
use the command line tool but yet they
could be using it every day at work I
rest my case all right so anyway that
did all the things necessary to get that
thing here so now all I have to do is CD
into it pretty cool huh that's why G git
lab has stolen it straight up and not
even Chang references to it in order to
do it because it's so freaking powerful
now it did a few things wrong for
example um it it actually named this
master instead of Main and so we're
going to fix that right
away uh this is a good thing uh get is
it get Branch I think it's is it get
Branch
DM uh main I think that's it yeah get
Branch DM main that changes it and then
we haven't saved anything here yet so
that's okay um and then what so we don't
we don't have a readme or anything in
here so let's actually go ahead and make
a read me really quick we're I promise
we're getting back to the bash I just
wanted to do take a note to do this so
we're going to did read me I'll say uh
uh my personal lab stuff
uh
mostly
messy or whatever right save it and then
what now we're going to save it so get
status these are commands that are all
going to go in your notebook right so
let's do okay so let's do get add dot if
you don't want to add an individual file
just add and get add dot just remember
that command it's a nice good one and
then get status will show you that it's
ready for committing and then you can go
um both M Mr misleading all branches
areal yeah I don't want to get into
that get commit dasm if you don't do the
dhm it'll dump you into this which is
fine but you know just do get commit
DM you can make that into an alias if
you want later and you it's just like
one command uh or you can make all of
this into a single Alias command called
Save which I'll show you about in a
second so you can do uh get commit and
you can say because we're just saving
stuff eventally we're not using get for
PRS and all the stuff that you'll
eventually learn but now it's just a
backup method so get commit DM it could
say uh update read me I I do think you
should have something relevantly you
know relative here so get
status uh all right what's going on why
is it taking so long am I dropping
frames this should never take that long
oh I don't know what happened
there okay so that it seems to be
get
status nothing to
commit what just
happened ad break the ad break is
loud I'm sorry the ad break is loud um I
I don't know what's going on
here I did not push
it I just changed it did it
automatically push
what is going
on what just happened
people it seems like it pushed
automatically I know it didn't show on
the get status that's what I'm I'm
seriously something is
weird something's not right
oh you know what it didn't show us
because it's never been pushed and it's
on Main that's why okay all right
because we changed the branch name yeah
no it's because we changed the branch
name that's what's going on okay I I I
I'm glad that happened live because I
changed it to Maine and Maine hasn't
been pushed to GitHub yet so GitHub
doesn't know about it so let's do this
let's do get yeah I can I can do the get
restore that that threw me that threw me
maybe that'll help somebody else because
it's like you don't have anything to
push it's like no this is totally fine
and that's because nothing to commit
you're working at tree clean because it
has no it doesn't know about it up on
GitHub yet
um what I did not know that all right so
here we go get
push uh and we're going to do get push
it's like nope can't push because
remember we did the renaming thing so we
need to do that so we get to get push D
you instead of that if you want to type
that you can I don't or origin Main and
that'll push it up
okay here we go uh get status now if we
make a change now uh mostly messy
stuff let's do the same thing again get
add dot get
commit
uh
stuff uh get status there it says you're
onee of main because it knows now it's
like synchronized it wasn't doing that
before and that threw me because I
hadn't pushed the branch yet so
um so here we go that we can do this we
can say get uh get push and that will
actually push it all up okay one last
thing to show you about what you can
eventually
do uh mostly messy stuff here is you can
eventually write a program like
this uh viic save we're going to get
there it's one of our projects one of
the projects that we're going to do is
we're going to write a we're going to
write a A bash program called save that
doesn't get saved for you and that is
one of our projects but right now you
can just type save add um add more stuff
to read me with no quotes or anything
and it'll actually do the commit the pay
and it also pulls down the latest so
that way you get you know a nice happy
log of all the commits said everything
you did so um I don't recommend my save
is actually so generic that if I don't
give it a title it just saves with a
comment called save I don't recommend
doing that for anything substantial but
for your you know for your home lab you
know notes and stuff there's really no
need for you to have a really extensive
commit memory and that kind of thing or
to ever Branch your PR and then merge it
back in and all those things you don't
need that this is just a honestly this
is just a method of backing your your
your code up um when you get to a
substantial project just know that you
can add on to this your get skills that
you have now you can add things onto the
top of that and you can do all those
other cool things but right now you
don't need it right now you just need it
as a backup mechanism and so um you
could use G stash yes so um G stashes is
a different thing um the G stash just
saves all your changes up into a stashed
thing locally uh that's only really a
Thing If you're trying to pull down
changes or you've made changes and you
want to keep them and then pull them
down and then thing but right none of
that is relevant right now because the
only thing we're doing in the lab is
we're bagging up our notes while
developing in bash so let's get back to
the bash coding we got another 40
minutes um uh so add add commit and push
is effectively only for the current
directory that you're in yeah yeah and I
I've never done that outside of the
directory um those are the main command
though eventually you're going to do a
get pull to get the latest changes but
you'd only need to do that if you made
changes to the repo someplace else right
and and by the way let's let's actually
take a very realistic situation where
you might do that let's do that Dale
okay so let's try this let's let's teach
you PLL in a relevant practical purpose
which is I thought about something I
don't have my terminal I'm on my phone
accessing the YouTube or the sorry the
get API uh the tool or I'm on another
computer and I just want to take a note
really quick and I want to have it back
at home on my terminal all right so
let's let's let's let's that's a very
real scenario so let's do that really
quick GitHub let's do get so let's going
to we're going to open the we're going
to open up the web page get repo view--
web that's going to open up your web
browser whether you're on WSL or or or
Linux or a Mac it's going to open up
this is the reason terminal velocity is
on your workstation system with an
integration not in some container or BM
because that wouldn't work that way
other than WSL which strictly speaking
is a BM so container personal lab stuff
so let's say let's say that you're
you're your your grandma's house and
Thanksgiving or something and and you
want to make a change that you know
you're talking to your Tech friends and
you know at the dinner table and they
tell you something you're like oh man I
need to take that down before I forget
so you either get out on your phone
which you can do you can get on your
phone and like thumb away all the little
notes that you wanted to do um or you
can you know um borrow their computer
but you obviously don't know how to SSH
into your home system yet so you don't
have your laptop with you you want want
to take a note you want to change
something through the web interface so
you come in here and you click on
there's a million things you can do here
um you can just click here and hit it
and then edit this one okay um I'm going
to cancel those changes if you this is
kind of a fun one but if you um uh you
can actually I used to I for a long time
this was how we did all of our coding
before I taught people them or anything
we just clicked on code right here and
we would say um wait code spaces okay uh
where is it where is it
um what is it it's like I think it's is
it dot
I think it's
dot there's someplace you can put dot I
can't remember which one it is there's a
way that you can actually make it
actually open it in um in in and and
edit it is
itev is it
one of the reasons that you should learn
GitHub when I do code Mage we're going
to learn vs code because it's built into
GitHub your extension GI reposit want to
sign in to get a
allow okay so it's signing in it's doing
all of its thing it's is it slash I
think it is slash that's the quick key
you're right it is slash it is
absolutely
slash all right so this extension wants
to access to get account uh I want to do
it as RBX Rob okay so now there's my
thing thing I can say uh I can go in
here and say that's the preview here's
the read me uh and I can put the dot now
so if you if you want to do terminal
editing
here and it's kind of slow I'm not going
to lie uh we'll put a period there all
right so you can actually save this and
where is save I forgot it's been so long
so here we go so this is so here is
going to tell you how to save it your
changes will be committed and
immediately pushed to the main branch on
GitHub don't show again commit and push
you can put a thing here it's like add
period you remember that comment thing
that I showed you same thing you just
put that there um all right so last
thing I want to practice here is I'm
almost positive so I was trying to
figure out the quick key for this and
somebody says it's slash so if you come
up here let's like refresh this right
refresh it's got a period let's say I
want to edit on it so I I push slash on
the page nope that's not it it's not it
I don't know which one it is I think
it's dot yes it's dot it's dot it's not
slash it's dot so how's that for a quick
key my friends that's dot I knew it was
dot I knew it was I couldn't remember
where to type the dot though so anywhere
on the web page like anywhere anywhere
on the web page if you just type dot
it'll open up that page in the local
editor and and throw you into it which
is pretty damn cool because it works
anywhere
and you know it's it's full-blown vs
code which is designed to be webif IED
so this you know why am I doing all this
because because this is a very real time
when you would make a change you know
especially around the holidays and now
you're screwed right because now you
just made this change Here and Now what
all right so what if you what if I go in
here and I'm making another change
another thing here what if I even put a
period here right and you're like I
swear to God I change that I'm going to
just add it here right okay but now
watch watch what happens now yeah get
add do get commit dasm add
period now we're going to have a
conflict get
push it's like oh
crap
right so so that that is not good right
we have a merge conflict oh no what are
we going to do right so we could do
instead it says oh okay so we're going
to try a get pull get pull it down it's
like oh my God what is this all about
okay this is because it doesn't know how
to resolve the changes in your two
things that you changed so we need to
set it up to do this I do the merg
rebase so get config um pull I swear
we're going to get back to the bash
um uh V web view absolutely you just
push the period and it'll OB
automatically load it pretty cool right
yes your poor computer I know it's
taking
forever all right so now let's do get
pull again and see if it's smart enough
to resolve the changes merge of the made
so it's making an automatic commit
you're like okay merge made get
stats all right so okay so it says we
have two commits to be made here so
let's actually go ahead and make those
get uh get
push all right so let's go open it again
GH uh repo view-- web let's go look at
it and we see here that it's there we
can actually click on um or is commit
history I'm trying to find a commit
history I think it's right here oh no
there it is see how it said six commits
you click on six commits and there's all
the all the commits and you can see what
they did and
everything okay um anyway so that has
been a situation where I I've made a
change and I want to do that we just C
discovered everything you need to know
about git uh there is one other case we
could use get stash if you've made
changes that you and you want to pull
down other changes so let's say you
wanted to do that and you could do a get
stash and that will store them and you
could do a get stash pop and you can go
look at that um but yeah so that's
that's the
thing uh save and start a new one for
bash yeah well it doesn't matter because
it's holiday it's this is all going in
Holiday boost so and yeah this this
video is going to get renamed into the
Boost video so um anyway here comes more
bash so now let's do bash um so Chloe
make sure to make a difference about
bash right here okay because this is a
thing uh the next 30 minutes we're going
to go back to bash um and so what do we
do we got a lab and we need to make some
stuff here so let's make our Fu file
again this is a good practice if you
haven't done this before go ahead and
recreate it you can copy it in if you
want if you have it in temp Fu you can
just copy it from temp Fu into Dot and
that'll move it into the current
directory which we don't have okay but
now we're going to go ahead and make a
new one so touch
Fu uh actually let's let's use a better
name let's call it greet how about that
we'll call it greet uh touch greet and
now we're going to
uh schmod plus x a
greet and you might want to start
putting all these you know stuff in here
uh it's like you could say we're going
to learn markdown you should have
already learned markdown so we're going
to say hod plus
x uh file and you could just I'm just
being you here so you know you can put
like a a note here and say uh make uh
text file
script into an executable
script all right so you put that there
you get the point right and so there we
go now you got greet
here and you can say okay so you know
your notes should be taking form my
friends you know like what is a shebang
line right what is a shebang line I'm
just giving you a sample of what you
could you know start
writing um and if you wanted to you know
you can put slash you know
hashbang uh anyway so anyway let's typ
GRE is affected by using space stash so
notes within a script is effective by
using space
Dash
space notes within a script oh comments
okay let's do a shebang line so shebang
line user benv why am I using user BNB
bash why am I doing that right and then
let's do a thing again let's
do uh langing we had langing equals
French you know you you you guys
remember the rest right
so um
then what we had case
laying
in and then we had uh
French uh and we had
um GRE
equals
um Russ
French I mean you could have it be
completely different here you could have
it have it be a screen if you want you
could say uh Sal
right all right so and then over
here
isach uh if it's not doing the coloring
the fastest thing is just close it and
reopen it
[Music]
um yeah I am absolutely anti-user B EnV
I am I hate it but but it makes sense if
you're writing scripts for all over for
everybody to use for yourself to use
it's fine it is for yourself for
yourself to use it it's fine if you
don't just know what you're getting into
and this is this is largely been
influenced by the fact that Homebrew is
in a different location and you don't
have transportable scripts so um we
talked about that
okay it is insecure it's completely
insecure yeah it's completely insecure
you should not do it for anything but
your own scripts because anybody can put
any program named bash in the path and
take over whatever you're doing if
you're putting it in a multiuser
environment you should never do this in
a multi-user environment do I need to
put that
there
uh never do this in anything but your
personal
scripts yeah I can say
how about that does that make you guys
happy I should probably have called that
I made a whole video about
this
yep
but fully qualified path and The Bash XE
it will break but you can't use the
script on wsl2 and Mac at the same time
that's what will happen and I don't want
that so I want to use my scripts on both
things so
if if Mac hadn't been completely stupid
and actually updated user b bash or then
we would be fine but we're not because
Apple's full of crap but we're little
left hold in the bag all right so I
reopened it and now it knows everything
so we have French here your greet
appears unused okay so um and then we
can do this we can
say uh how about this greeting
so then we can say
Echo uh
greeting um and we can put the world in
here we did this already but let's just
catch up again so there's the
world
um
Russian actually let's do
Spanish Spanish is
Ola and I'm just going to have the three
because I don't want to waste time on
that I I could do Russian but I feel bad
because I'm not actually writing Russian
so French and Spanish let's just keep
that for now
um okay so let's see here you got you
got this you got this now wouldn't it be
really nice to be able to reuse it so
let's say uh if you have a
greeting and you know but wouldn't it be
nice if we could ask him what their name
is so let's do that how let's this is
the first moment of interactivity that
we're we're going to add so pay
attention we got a 30 minutes in here
we're going to try to keep it so
wouldn't it be great if we could
actually ask them what their name is so
where would we even put that we can put
it at the beginning up here we can put
it down here this is where our code
organization kind of gets interesting
right so let's put it up here it would
be sequentially it would be up here so
let's put it up here and let's say we
want to ask a word here so we want to
say um and this is where we're going to
use the read command so read
uh we could actually do this I mean you
can probably figure this out you can say
Echo uh actually let's do this let's
say how about let's
say
um let's say this let's say
greeting
uh let's do this let's let's make this
more fun
trying to remember how I used to do it
so's say
Echo hello
there uh what's your
name
okay and let's go back to our
enr what what happened to my bachelor
C did I kill my
bashy please tell me I
didn't I
did what the hell
happened did I do it live did I wipe out
my home directory
live I think I did
where did my Christmas hey hi I'm making
a
video oh my gosh what is it my safety
kit my reload a thing okay I'll do the
thing I just blew away my my
thing
lot okay CD dot I'm like freaking out
right
now what the hell did I
do did I run on
accident cleaning up files I don't
know I don't have a Bach see anymore I
have no idea where it
went oh it's pointing to dot
two oh you know what it was I was
cleaning out I was cleaning out my home
directory I don't know how I managed to
do
that yeah this is this is not this is
this is just me this is fine the files
are all still there I just I got a
little overzealous on my clean up so by
the way this is how the reason you
should write a DOT script right so now I
to get them all back I just have to run
set up again and everything comes back
including my my westerm stuff so um
let's do this let's do exec bash
DL yeah now it's like totally messed
up yeah
okay I well did you see how it resized
everything yeah that was kind of
fun anyway so that's why you want to
have your do in a script so you can get
your stuff
back your your files more than yeah I
mean that's
that's that's what I just did so this is
why you need a DOT files people it did
it added back the colors it it it fixed
a bunch of things so that's why you want
a do files good good little you know
world of the story there um we we are
going back into lab what sample so
all right so here we are and now um I
can go ahead and um run it uh in fact I
think I think I have did it kill my
colors let me just Che I want to check
no I'm still got them okay
um so what are we doing here well we
came in here because we wanted to run
the program so ENT in case you don't
remember it ENT uh bash DZ clear and
then we're going to run it SLG greet
that says run the program right here
here and we're going to only run the
program when the program updates that's
what that does so now we got Salo okay
so and the font size is a little bit
smaller than I would like let's go Zoom
it in a little
bit oh all right
so are you guys in this oh
God it it seems like it resized a
bit yeah
left drag look at that it even said the
left drag thing that's
[Music]
cool I know you guys
are frustrated by
my all right here we
go uh Echo greeting what time is it we
got
time so Echo greeting it's just echoing
the greeting but it's not doing anything
because there's no French we have French
equals greeting Salo greeting we want to
have we want to have like a name here
but there is no
name right wouldn't it be great if we
could get a name all right enter the
read command so
read um
name all right so now
what now it's going to prompt me from
the name here so now I have to type in a
name say Rob and it says Salo
Rob all right we got some commas in here
and stuff we don't
need so let's get rid of
that what's your name uh
Rob
um why is it doing that space
thing
greeting why is it doing the extra
space oh right so
hola how about that type the name in
yeah yeah the entire day to get to read
I know people it's
hard so what does Reed do Reed reads one
line of text from input that's it and it
does not care about spaces and stuff so
it'll put the spaces in there what does
that mean so like if I it says read that
so this is actually a shell check thing
read without Das will mangle backslashes
remember all those backslashes and stuff
we were doing so just always do do R but
there's actually one last one other
thing you could do I'm not going to do
this but you can do this you can do p
here and put both of these into a single
Command right if you if you want to do
this this is why it's a little hard
though because you got to put it up here
and you know like this and and that does
the same thing so the P the P does the
same thing it's just prompt in in one
one line if you if you prefer writing it
all in one line like that you can
there's absolutely nothing wrong with
writing both of this as two separate
commands in my opinion uh wait with
didn't we we got rid of name see this is
why I don't like it because it's too
hard to get to the text to edit it so I
tend to do this I tend to just Echo
whatever I'm going to say or print up it
or something and then just write it
afterwards and just just leave off the-
P so um you know wait let's do d a s
oops no it doesn't work there that's
weird
DT cool there we
go and I that's just that's just my
preference but you
know and
R Sal Rob okay we're gonna get to the
next thing
now wait what am I doing all right so
right so so there there we go and you
know um it it this is now about this
time it gets kind of fun to add color
right wouldn't it be fun if we could
distinguish um if we could distinguish
the
color so let's start talking about
terminal colors really quickly I'm not
going to get into the deep seeded parts
of this um if you want to in my do files
there is a command called uh term Coler
and so you can actually run it here I'm
doing the bang bang to do the inclusion
I did Exclamation point Exclamation
point term
colors
and wait what where where did
our we lost
our we lost our our screen
keys
huh interesting
screen sorry guys I gotta look at this
up NM screen key equals
one I something about my bash he killed
my my screenies I don't know what it
is I don't know we don't have time we
got to finish this all right so anyway
here's the color so we got our colors
back so this this is
Bash and and this is this is posing so
we're going to delete that daf or daap
to delete
it and so we got all these colors but
we're not necessarily using them so
let's comment out the ones we're not
using now you can do this and you could
this is one of those cases where you
could use visual
mode um or you could just you know do
them all at
once see so you know you can do the
whole thing or you can do them all at
once if you want to do them all at once
it's like this I I don't have my screen
keys I don't have my screen keys it's
not even worth doing this if I don't
have my screen keys
on I killed
[Music]
them
um why isn't my screen keys on
I killed him
somehow wait is it just off the screen
oh my God it's been on the whole time
and I just had my screen keys were too
high God I'm glad I showed you that the
whole time time it was working and I
just couldn't see it because I was
looking at the same thing as you guys
are looking at it was there the whole
time it's time for me to stop streaming
it is it's time for me to stop streaming
friends all right so we're going to do
this boom boom and we're going to send
CMT which is a program I'll show you how
to make and that'll automatically
comment out everything but let's say
that we want this to be cyan so let's
enable cyan and we'll do cyan
here okay so got to have a space uhoh
but what if
we
um yeah oh hey look it's all Canan now
hello oh but we don't want the the words
to be
Canan so let's change that by the way
you see how it shot them together there
there's another way to do this and that
is by wrapping it in curly brackets
right there called
mustaches and hello what's your name now
we don't want that part to be the same
color so we're going to put a reset in
here and you can look up these values um
you just have to look them up these are
special terminal escapes that we won't
get into but they send invisible
sequences to your computer
so that it you know makes colors on your
terminal that's the takeaway so now it's
this let's let's make their input really
special though so let's make their the
color of their input maybe you know gold
so let's put yellow here if we put
yellow let's go use
yellow uh and then after we take this we
got to make sure to Echo a reset to the
screen otherwise it'll all be yellow
from that point on so we're going to
Echo a reset and then we're going to
undo
yellow and enable that and now when when
they do their
[Music]
thing uh you can you can do that hey how
are you do so um so Rob all right it
didn't do my
yellow Why didn't it do my
yellow it didn't do my
yellow I wonder if I have to do a dasp
with this
I don't know let's
check Rob yeah there we
go all right so actually I think
um I think this one should also work I
don't think I just
reset all right yeah okay so you see how
it's like Rob and it say s Rob um and
then we can make anything it says color
as well but uh the point of this is is
that you can you can add color and by
adding so here's in generally how the
colors work is you add a color signal
and then you have to have a reset but
you can also change the color and then
eventually have a reset that's all it
really takes to to do color and you can
do all kinds of fun things with that so
I wanted to show it to you it does make
your interface slightly more fun um you
can get into ANC escapes we're not going
to do that there's literally you can do
millions of colors I suggest you don't
do anything more than these standard
colors because they're supported on any
terminal ever um that has color so so
there you go all right so that's been
enough of that but this wouldn't it be
great if we could like put all of this
we want to do something else so let's
say I don't know what if this was the
beginning of a story game an interactive
Story game like maybe we wanted to ask
them something fun after this right and
use their name but we want to do
something after this so we want to say
you know Echo uh do something
else and you know and maybe maybe we
don't want to we want to test that other
thing and this whole name thing is is
stopping us from writing the next code
because it's getting in way in the way
and um so that's kind of a problem right
so it's like you know our interactive
test is kind of just broken because it's
like constantly stuck on this
interaction wouldn't it be great if we
could just turn that hard offer now
because we got it working and this is
where functions and they're technically
sub routines functions sub routines and
procedures come in so this is one of
those terminology things so the the
terms that we're going to use here is is
the generalized term and I'm going to
get crap for saying this but it's better
the generalized term for a block of code
that is kind of set aside to do
something when you want it to is called
a sub ret
and that term is very very general and
the people that are going to complain
are going to are me talking about
functions no yes and no right are you
talking about procedures yes and no are
you talking about methods yes and no so
if you know what those other things are
all of those things qualify as
subroutines they're they're just code
that you put away steps instructions
that you've set aside somehow to be
called later right and at the very very
low level in assembly they're called
called sub routines so that what we're
doing so we want to take those steps
that we just did we want to group those
steps together into what we'll call a
sub routine for now um very frequently
you'll see the keyword function
associated with this even though if you
know functions from math you know that a
function always has output and and
people kind of use the term function in
bastardized ways in in Computing for
lots of reasons that we'll get into
another day so so for right now what
we're going to do is we're going to say
we want to put what how much of this do
we want to put in here so how about this
whole prompt your name thing right let's
can that be a group of things let's do
that so let's call that what should we
call it let's say
uh I don't know what's I usually like to
start these with a verb so
prompt uh prompt for name and right away
somebody just yelled at me and said you
can't use dashes in name
you absolutely can you can use dashes
and names because this is Bash you can
in Shell but you can in bash and we're
writing bash code and we are never going
to write posic Shell Code because
there's no reason to if you need to go
back in time and write a posit sh script
so that it'll run on some esoteric ax
machine and there are many reasons you
would need to do that be my guest but
you have bash you get to use bash so in
this case we're going to use bash this
is not the kind of program that I'm
going to be running that needs to be
compatible with every system out there
that is a separate topic and yes that's
a valuable thing um there are lots of
reasons to write posic shell scripts out
there none of them apply here the very
nature of the reason that I use user bnv
is because I'm writing a script for
myself on my own computer the same
reason that I'm using neovim the same
reason that I'm using t-mo the same
reason that I'm using West term on my
machine and not a container or a VM
and there's going to be a lot of Linux
and Unix people that going to see this
video and go what the hell this is this
is not proper training for Unix you
should only teach them posic scripts you
know Reon I'm not doing that the first
reason is you posic scripts are insecure
and this number two reason is they're
not that compatible as you think and
they're also not needed everywhere so
it's more important that you write your
script in bash to begin with and then
downgrade it if necessary to put it on
something else and that is a very modern
approach I understand that there are a
bunch of Boomers who just lost their
because I said that that's okay
that's the way I'm teaching you to do it
that's the way you should do it if you
want to do it some other way that's fine
but you're totally F fine to do this
it's easier to understand it's easier to
write and it's totally legit somebody
else is going to tell you that you need
to put a function keyword here you don't
you don't need it you can just write
this it's faster to WR it's convenient
it's easy for you to process hell we're
using ANC colors here you would put that
in a professional posix Unix script to
be deployed to ax systems on millions of
machines you should be able to do that
but not at this time that's not what
bashes for uh uh so you need to
downgrade you want to use the in this
case the whole Progressive enhancement
thing about learning shell first and
then learning bash second I've changed
my opinion on that I used to do that I
did that for 10 years I taught people
that was what I did I don't do that
anymore because because it's more
important for you to learn first and
then downgrade when necessary and if you
need to upgrade you can upgrade to Pearl
or to python or a ruby or to go or to
rust or anything later so bash is a
really great Center language for your
own personal script archive and then you
if you decide that you want to take
pieces of that and put them in your
production deployment then you can
decide what pieces can stay and what
can't okay you would never put color
there for example probably you would
never make it interactive right because
it would block and stop your automations
from working so I'm that I had to put
that there because I'm going to get
for this um so next okay we're almost
done here we're at 52 minutes so we got
we got a prompt for a
name now we we're going to go ahead what
about this all this language stuff what
is that all about right so uh H how
should we do that so what if we just put
all of this stuff this really doesn't
belong belong in why don't we put this
at the very top so we'll put it up here
um it's actually more important than
these other things so we'll put it at
the top so people coming to the Lang to
the program can go change it spoiler
alert that kind of thing is set by the
system so you don't even need that um
you could just change it for the entire
system um okay so next we have this kind
of lingering code let's put that around
into something uh what should we call
that let's say um what should we say we
could say
uh well let's actually call it greet
let's call this one
greet all right okay so we're going to
say greet
name greeting name but now now we have a
problem how do we get name where does
that come from we have the proper name
up here and that sets it and then down
here is it going to work it actually is
going to work and um
but it's not going to be what you think
and and this is going to this is kind of
a problem with shell
coding um so let's go ahead and get into
it um let's go ahead and start our our
test
again all right so it says do something
so it just went right ahead and did
something what happened it didn't run my
program right that's what we wanted it
doesn't do anything until you tell it
you wanted to do
something uh uh okay yeah it thinks do
as a program as a thing so I'll put that
in a string so it's not doing the other
things because we didn't call them we
put them in the groups but we haven't
called them so I can actually do this I
can say prompt tab tab oh it's not
seeing my prompt yeah I have a question
I wonder if it would do it if I did it
like
this I'm just going to see if my my
completion works this way I don't think
it
does no prompt
nope it
doesn't yeah I this is a shell problem I
think if I had tree Setter it probably
do it better but I don't I don't care
right
now all right so we need to have prompt
Doh for name which I don't know why it's
not doing normally it would if You tab
tab it'll give it to you but it's not
for some
reason that's an I don't know why it's
not doing that
it should it should have done that
so I I broke my my viim somehow I don't
know anyway PR for name that's just
running it and then after we get the
prom for name we can say greet so
that'll be the next
thing right so you know and if you want
to you can put a line here if it makes
it easier you could say like main or
something right and I'm going to put
this
here I have a little script that does
that
and put the little lines in there so
this stuff so here's all your function I
mean functions procedures whatever you
sub routines whatever you want to call
them they're all up there and then down
here we've got we got the actual main
program that's running and spoiler
alerts in some languages there's
actually another function called Main in
this case it's implied it's implied that
that's main but I put main there just so
you get the feel for it and as you can
see you can mix it up with calling these
other sort of little programs they very
much are like little programs inside of
the bigger program um that's why they're
called sub routines and and or
procedures whatever language you're
using it depends but um so so let's go
down you can see there's some problems
here though right because it's here it
said prompt for name but it's doing
prompting for name is it actually doing
it right it says read the name and then
Echo reset for the thing and then it
keeps on going so let's go see if we can
get it to do what it's supposed to do
here all right so actually we're just
going to run it this
time
soget yeah rtfm yes and here we have
promp for name command not found because
I did the wrong
name I typed it wrong so it's prompt to
for name so let's go down here
greet hey let's see what is your name
Rob uh sadly Rob do something else all
right so this is something that's both
scary and good and we're going to
introduce the idea of concept of scope
and that'll be the last thing for today
so this here group this function here
has a variable called name and it might
be intuitive to say that oh yeah since
that since this group of you know
instructions was executed first since
this sub routine was run first therefore
down here it knows about name if if we
did it in the opposite order it wouldn't
know about it obviously I mean it would
be weird but let's try it anyway and see
what happens let's try to change the
order and run it that way if we do it
that way it says salute nobody and then
Rob and then it just throws it on the
ground right so it is true that that
variable as long as it's in the right
order gets you know does the right
thing but there's a problem this is
technically kind of bad because you
don't want everything in the global
space and and this is another reason to
use bash instead of posix what I'm about
to do cannot be done in posix
Shell everything is what's called a
global in posic Shell that means all
variables are readable by everybody in
the entire
program and you might not know why
that's a bad thing yet but suffice it to
say that you have variable Collision so
maybe you'll make another group of
program of of instructions you know set
of instructions that wants to use the
name name well now you can't because the
other one that you don't even know
remember that you made and right now
we're using the same file but as soon as
you start using multiple files which is
kind of dubious when you're talking
about shell anyway but let's say you did
then you might have somebody's name is
colliding with your other name and the
other one is blowing it away okay so now
this is the first time to introduce the
idea of scope to you and this is going
to be the end of this video variables
scope so I wanted to get to the function
thing the procedures the sub routines
thing and to the idea of scope variable
scope what this means is that when I
these remember I said these are like
little programs inside of the other
program it's really key that you think
about that but in terms of like let's
try to make them even more like
encapsulated right and this idea is
called encapsulation so encap that means
everything is all contained within that
block a block by the way is everything
between the curly brackets right the
curly brackets identifies the Block in
this case so you can have blocks for
conditions like an if in case like we
saw you can have blocks for you know
procedures of sub routines and functions
like we have right now so a block is
just any any grouping of instructions or
commands inside of of you know in this
case the the the the curly brackets
right so what we want to do is we want
to really make this really lock down
which means we have to say if I have
name I'm going to lock it down right now
we know we're going to have a problem
because we have to exchange between the
two so how do we do that well the first
thing we need to do is we need to start
declaring what things are so now in
order to do that we have name right well
since we're now inside of a of a sub
routine we'll call it um you can do this
you can say
local uh name and that will Define the
name to be local but immediately we're
going to break something by doing that
so what we just said is that only this
block can see name only the block now
obviously we're going to need it down
below I'm going to show you how to do
that but but Watch What Happens now if I
type rob it doesn't know it why because
we just protected ourselves by declaring
that this thing is local now in Shell in
Shell because of the the the history of
shell everything by default is global
everything is global and anybody will
tell you that that is a really bad idea
and python you have to declare you know
everything's local by default every
other language on the planet besides
shell assumes localized scope every
other programming language on the planet
assumes local scope for safety reasons
and shell does not not shell does not
because it's a practical thing and it's
ancient it's ancient so bash is
inherited from pic shill and and Bash at
least came along and said you know what
posic shell is ridiculously hard to
write anything Inc in fact if you go
look at Old posic Shell scripts you'll
just like shake your head like what the
hell is going on because they would
literally create like these big
environment variables just to hold the
return values of everything and just
kind of have to just agree not to stomp
on each other nobody wants that that's
like a really bad idea so if you're
going to write bash code do it right and
start by defining the scope of your
variables by doing it this way right now
if you actually want a variable to be
everywhere you can do that you could do
it this instead so here's one option you
can say declare instead of local you can
say declare name now name is like known
to be a global that everybody's going to
use and now every I mean it's it's no
different than it was before but the
difference is that now it's explicitly
declared that it's like hey I'm going to
use this thing and I'm going to reuse it
and there it goes it works again that's
probably where you should leave this but
the last thing I want to show you is how
to communicate from one thing into the
next thing and and that is a very useful
skill in bash and there's a lot of Unix
uh Unix Shi programmers are going to
really roll over and there you know and
attack me when I talk about this but but
we're going to do it anyway so we're
going to declare name as a private thing
right right and we're going to actually
this is where we start to coming into
subshells so it says so we read the name
right hello there what is your name and
it prints out some cool stuff and then
it prints out the name right now well
actually I take it back in this case we
have to do the declare I this is a good
place to end the video because we're
doing the prompt and we can't read the
the thing from the prompt so this is the
this is a good one to do that um but you
could do this you could say there's one
last thing we could do let's say promper
name how about how about we do this how
about we do read name we could do that
right so
um yeah I'm trying to
think no I think this is better as a
global I could just keep this as a
global this is a good
one well because this this will be a
good introduction to functions later and
we can I can show you how to do a
function in an actual function so let's
we haven't done that yet but let's go
ahead so let's say declare uh let's just
do declare name we're going to say I'm
going to use it everywhere and then
that'll be the end of this video so we
have a prompt we have a
greet and um and you know the rest is a
thing now it does say the did the
language is actually also kind of global
isn't it now we could say we could do a
couple things here we could make
language local so we could say greet in
a specific language right uh or we could
make it so that um I mean it's up to you
but you could also do it so that we
declare you know we also
declare uh laying up here now this is
the language is
French this is actually one of those
cases where Shel will usually complain
no it doesn't Okay so there we go it
declar the language equals French
declare the name as a thing and so now
we have the Declaration of global
variables at the top and that is good
because you are always going to have
Global variables and Global meaning that
they're visible to everything in the
system and um this is why we're talking
about this in terms of procedures sub
routines and state and uh we will
eventually get to functional programming
where this kind of thing is a big no no
but you don't understand that
particularly yet but that's what we'll
talk about next time we'll talk about
how does set up like an a function
versus a procedure both of them are sub
routines but what is the difference and
we'll talk about that next and then um
we'll start to program and we can
continue to do all of this in bash okay
so that's going to be it for me today I
am going to be doing some more videos
tomorrow uh so we'll pick up on this
probably first thing tomorrow and
um uh I I assume I'm going to be done
for the night but um so if you if you
want to go ahead and start playing
around with this one last thing before
we leave this we made a lot of changes
we don't want them to get destroyed
let's go ahead and add those changes
back to so we're going to get add dot so
that's everything in here get status to
see what I changed and you see I have
those two programs to change get commit
dasm uh add initial
greet and then get uh actually we could
do yeah get push and then that will push
it up and if you want to go look at it
get Depo view-- web that'll open it up
and again if you wanted to change this
stuff just a reminder you can do it in
your own thing so there's the get
program right here you can click on the
GRE program it'll actually show you your
all your really cool code that you just
wrote and this the really cool thing is
that when you open up like this now
watch when I push a
dot boom I push the dot and it opens up
the editor and it loads the code I mean
that's pretty damn
cool I'm not going to lie that's pretty
damn cool so like if you're over the
holiday if you want to continue to do
your practice and you just have a
computer or you want use somebody else's
computer you can just go over there as
long as you're logged into GitHub and
and you can work on your project and
this is why this is why I think having
GI up or somebody who's learning is a
great idea not only that but you can
share it with a mentor of yours and have
them look at it and stuff um is it true
that you could have do done this all on
your own computer using like uh a bear
git repo absolutely and if you're a
hacker you might eventually prefer to do
things like that that don't have any
access to the public but for now you're
fine for now you can find you can share
it and if you decide to go public with
it you can so that's the end of this
video today we'll continue to keep
coding through bash until we finish uh
um but you already know a lot you
already know uh how my clone function
procedure sub routine Works in in my
bashor St so you're you're going getting
to the point where you're going to be
able to read about that uh so we'll see
you next time